地球脉动 III
字幕翻译：村儿南
这里是非洲中部的沙漠绿洲
This is Guelta d'Archei in Central Africa.
一片不毛之地
A hostile, seemingly empty world.
却孕育着生命
There is life here.
这里的生命时时刻刻处于危机之中
But it exists at the very limits of survival.
因为这是一个水资源极度缺乏的世界
For this is a world with almost no water.
像这样的土地覆盖了地球上超过三分之一的面积
Lands like these cover over a third of our planet.
在这里 生命被迫另辟蹊径
Here, life is forced to do things differently.
第三集
沙漠与草原
这里是最古老的沙漠
This is the most ancient desert of all.
纳米布沙漠 坐落于非洲西南部
The Namib - in south west Africa.
是地球上最热的地方之一
It is one of the hottest places on Earth.
尽管如此 这只雄性鸵鸟和它的伴侣
Yet this male ostrich and his mate
依然来到了这里组建家庭
have come here to start a family.
很少有捕食者会在白天冒着炎热觅食
Few predators venture out during the heat of day.
但这种安全是需要付出代价的
But such safety comes at a price.
刚孵化出的雏鸟暴露在烈日之下
Out in the open, the newly-hatched chicks are exposed to the crushing heat of the sun.
然而有些雏鸟还没孵化出来
But not all of the brood have hatched.
在全部孵化出来前 一家子都将留在这里
Until they do, the family will stay here.
成年鸵鸟轮流负责保护雏鸟
The adults take it in turns to protect the brood.
当轮到雌鸵鸟休息时
So whilst the female takes a well-earned break,
雄鸵鸟就会接手这项辛苦的工作
the male takes over for the most testing shift.
它轻轻的晃动尚未破壳的蛋
He gently rolls the unhatched eggs...
呼唤里面的雏鸟
..calling to the young within them.
它不想落下任何一个孩子
He doesn't want to leave anyone behind.
温度持续上升 每个小时升高5摄氏度
The temperature continues to rise by five degrees Celsius every hour.
雄鸵鸟用身体挡住太阳
He protects the chicks that have emerged...
保护刚出生的雏鸟
..shading them with his own body.
经受太阳一整天的炙烤后
At the end of another gruelling day in the sun...
雄鸵鸟已经精疲力竭
..he's lost almost all his energy.
但它必须克制住想要休息的冲动
But he must resist the urge to rest.
凉爽的夜晚能缓解些许疲劳
The cool of the night brings some relief...
但同时捕食者也开始了活动
..but now predators are out and about.
这将是个漫长的夜晚
It's going to be a long night.
黎明时分 惊喜悄然而至
Dawn brings a surprise.
家庭增添了三名新成员
Three additions to the family...
跟刚回来的妈妈打个招呼
..to greet the returning female.
但有一个难题
But there's a problem.
在如此高温下 雏鸟很难存活
The chicks won't survive another day in these temperatures.
然而雄鸵鸟并不准备离开此处
Yet the male is reluctant to leave.
因为仍有些蛋没有孵化出来
Some of the eggs have still not hatched.
然而时间已经所剩无几
But time has run out.
必须离开了
They must depart.
就差了几分钟没赶上
Just a few minutes too late.
缺少了父母的保护
Alone and without the protection of its parents,
这只雏鸟的生存机会十分渺茫
this hatchling's chances are slim.
在沙漠中生存
Survival here, as in all deserts,
生命如履薄冰
is on a knife edge.
因此 沙漠的居民必须以非凡的方式进化
So desert dwellers have had to evolve in remarkable ways.
其中有些生物成了龙与独角兽传说的源头
Some have even given rise to legends of dragons and unicorns.
甚至贫瘠的沙丘也有其独到的特质
And even the dunes have their own magical quality.
事实上 有些沙丘能发出属于自己的声音
Indeed some have their own voice.
在阿拉伯半岛 这种非同寻常的声音
Here in Arabia, this extraordinary sound
是由数十亿沙粒相互振动而产生的
is created by billions of moving sand grains vibrating against one another.
在这片世界上最大的沙漠中 这种诡异的旋律可以传到数里以外
The eerie song they produce can be heard for miles across the world's biggest sand desert.
风也将沙子吹成了各种离奇的形状
Winds have also built sand into surreal shapes.
世界各地 如此奇异的沙漠几乎如同外星世界
Deserts around the world can appear so alien, that they seem to belong to another planet altogether.
其中最奇异的当属澳大利亚的这片沙漠
Few more so than here in Australia.
然而仍有一个小家伙选择了这里
Yet one little creature chooses this desert
来为它生命中最重要的环节做准备
to prepare for a most important event in its life.
一只雄性斑大亭鸟
A male spotted bowerbird.
在过去的两个月里
For the last two months,
它一直在等待短暂降雨
he has been busy in anticipation of brief rains...
只有那时 雌鸟才会寻找配偶
That is when females will look for a mate.
为此雄鸟搭建了一个亭台 类似一种剧院
So he's built a bower, a sort of theatre,
如果雌鸟愿意 它们将在这个舞台上共舞
a stage on which he will dance with a female, if she is willing.
雄鸟用成堆的蜗牛壳和骨头点缀舞台入口
He decorates the entrance with piles of empty snail shells and bones.
没有雌性能拒绝这一切
How could any female resist?
随时都有可能下雨
The rains are due any day,
所以这是雄鸟改善装潢的最后机会
so it's his last chance for improvements.
蜗牛壳永远都不嫌多
You can never have too many shells.
但当它离开的时候
But in his absence...
一只竞争对手来到此处 评估一下彼此的优劣
..a rival male drops by, to size up the competition...
再搞点破坏
..and cause trouble.
破坏对手的舞台
Wreck your neighbour's bower
就等于完善自己的舞台
and your own might look better.
再顺走点儿好看的装饰物
And perhaps one of the best bits would look good in his bower.
主人回来了
The owner is back.
有点儿不对劲
And something isn't right.
抓紧时间修缮
Repairs are needed.
依然没有雨水或是雌鸟的影子
Still no sign of rain or females.
但它没有气馁 而是继续准备
Undeterred, he continues his preparations.
是时候排练求爱表演了
Time to rehearse his courtship display.
然而遗憾的是 这只雄鸟也许永远只能独舞
But sadly he may only ever dance alone.
在过去的三年里 这里没有下过一场雨
For the last three years, the rains have failed.
而没有雨 雌鸟便不会寻找配偶
Without them, the females won't mate.
成立一个家庭需要雨水来提供食物
They need the rains to provide food for their family.
气候的变化正在影响这些鸟类
Changes in the climate are affecting these birds,
同时也在影响我们人类
just as they are affecting us.
世界上四分之一的人口居住在干旱地区
A quarter of the world's people live in arid lands.
因此我们也必须应对气候的变化
So we, too, have to deal with climate change.
降雨量的减少与旱期的延长使沙漠区域得以扩张
Less rainfall and extended droughts allow deserts to grow.
与此同时 一种自然中最令人生畏的现象之一的
And as they do, so does the likelihood
发生几率也大大上升
of one of nature's most intimidating events.
沙尘暴
A dust storm.
一堵近两公里高的由沙尘构筑的墙
A wall of dust up to a mile high,
速度达到每小时110公里
travelling at almost 70mph.
如今这些破坏性风暴是有史以来最强大的风暴之一
Today these destructive storms are some of the most powerful ever seen.
势不可挡的沙尘暴穿越数千公里
Unstoppable, they can travel thousands of miles...
压垮世界各处的城镇
..overwhelming towns and cities across the world...
以迅雷不及掩耳之势
..in an instant.
生命需要数千年的时间才能适应沙漠的极端环境
It takes millennia for life to adapt to the extremes of deserts.
这群狒狒生存于地球上最干燥的环境之一
These baboons manage to survive in one of the driest environments on Earth.
纳米比亚的埃龙戈区
The Erongo region in Namibia.
这里已经足有八个月没下过一滴雨了
Not a single drop of rain has fallen here for eight months.
这群狒狒在这里的生活十分艰难
Life here for these baboons is as hard as it gets.
对于这只年轻的雌性狒狒来说尤为艰难
And it's especially difficult for this young female.
它刚产下第一个孩子
She has just given birth to her first baby.
雌狒狒非常迫切的需要水
She's desperate for water.
没有水 它便无法产奶
Without it, she can't produce milk.
食物中含有的少量水分
The tiny of amount of moisture in her food
根本不足以满足这对母子的需要
is simply not enough for both of them.
狒狒群必须不断寻找水源
The troop must constantly search for water.
不会为了雌狒狒停下脚步
And they won't wait for her.
终于 一只狒狒在岩石表面发现了一条细流
At last, one of the troop's scouts finds a tiny trickle on a rock face.
可以松一口气了
Relief!
但这些水还不够
But not for everyone.
年轻的雌狒狒只能先等待
The young mother will have to wait.
地位决定了喝水的顺序
Access to the precious water is determined by rank.
雌狒狒的地位如此之低
She is so low in the pecking order...
甚至可能完全喝不上水
..she might fail to get any drink at all.
因为插队会受到严厉的惩罚
Because jumping the queue is severely punished.
虽然风险很高 但雌狒狒不能再等了
It's risky, but she can't wait any longer.
一步险招
A dangerous move.
但母亲的决心战胜了一切
But there's no match for a mother's determination.
这些水足以保证它和孩子能坚持到下次降雨
This will be enough to keep her and her baby alive until rain falls.
雨水不仅能拯救狒狒群
Rain brings salvation not just to her and the troop,
还将拯救这片干涸的大地
but to the thirsty land.
雨水可以重塑沙漠
When it does fall, it can transform a desert.
将沙漠变成地球上最富有生产力的生态系统
And turn it into one of Earth's most productive landscapes.
草原
Grasslands.
草原是地球上最大的
They support the greatest concentrations of large animals
大型动物聚集地
to be found anywhere on the planet.
这里展现着大自然最为壮观的一面
Here nature is at its most spectacular.
尽管看起来很难相信
This leopardess, believe it or not,
但这只豹子已经做好了随时启动捕猎的准备
is ready to hunt at a moment's notice.
它是少有的几只学会了如何隐藏在树顶
She is one of the few special leopards that have learnt to hide in the tree tops,
并等待猎物送上门来的豹子之一
and wait for their prey to come to them.
悄无声息
Without making a sound,
它已经就位了
she gets into position.
这次没能成功
Not this time.
现在周围所有动物都知晓它的存在了
And now her presence is known to all.
但豹子为了成功 会付出惊人的努力
But leopards will go to astonishing lengths to succeed.
而有些豹子的胆量尤为突出
And some are more daring than others.
这只豹子爬到9米高的树枝上
This leopard climbs up to a branch nine metres above the ground.
这里的高度比两层楼还高
She's higher than the roof of a two-storey house.
从如此高的地方跳下去很可能会危及自己的生命
Leopards have killed themselves jumping from these heights.
想要在热带草原上独当一面
To succeed on these equatorial grasslands,
就必须有着极强的适应性和过人的胆识
you must be adaptable and sometimes brave.
欧亚大草原
The Eurasian Steppe,
地球上最大的草原
the largest grassland on earth.
动物在这里接受着不同的考验
It tests animals in a different way.
这里的风速可以达到每小时近130公里
Here, the wind can blow at speeds of nearly 80mph.
气温可以降至零下30摄氏度以下
And temperatures drop to below minus 30 degrees Celsius.
然而 一种奇异的生物进化出了
Yet one bizarre creature has evolved
在这种极端环境下生存的方式
ways to survive in these extremes.
高鼻羚羊
Saiga antelope.
是一种健壮的小型动物 曾与猛犸象生活在同一个时代
Small but tough animals that lived alongside woolly mammoths.
雄性高鼻羚羊巨大的鼻子既能过滤灰尘
The male's enormous nose both filters out the dust
又能将吸入的冷空气变温暖
and warms up the cold air before it reaches his lungs.
但每年的这个时候 鼻子还有个特别的用途
But at this time of year, it also serves a very different purpose.
那就是吸引雌性
It impresses the females.
鼻子越大 魅力越大
And the bigger it is, the better.
这只年长的雄性高鼻羚羊知道如何吸引雌性的注意
This old male knows what it takes to hold their attention.
但似乎还得加把劲
But they make him work for it.
如果收效甚微
And if that isn't effective,
那就来点别的招式
he has other ways of impressing them.
头顶一从灌木 威严十足
A bush - very majestic.
然而当你位居高位 称王称雄时
But when you are king of the steppe,
总会有挑战者虎视眈眈 觊觎你的王位
there's always someone waiting to claim your crown.
这只年轻的高鼻羚羊认为自己可以一试
This young buck fancies his chances.
它的目标是羚羊首领的眷群
He aims to steal the king's harem.
挑战者冲锋 准备战斗
The challenger charges, ready to do battle.
这可能会是一场殊死搏斗
This could be a fight to the death.
发情期中的雄性羚羊有70%会失去生命
70% of rutting males will die.
年长的雄羚羊最终开始占据上风
The older male eventually begins to gain the upper hand.
最后一击
And with one final effort,
它赶跑了这名年轻的对手
he drives the young rival away.
羚羊群之王守住了王位
The king has kept his crown -
以及它的眷群
and his harem.
只有最强壮的高鼻羚羊才能在这片
Only the strongest saigas can endure and succeed
地球上最严酷的环境之一顽强的生存下去
in one of the harshest places on Earth.
而在赤道附近 阳光和水资源得到了保障
But close to the equator, where there is constant warmth and water,
这里有着天堂般的广袤草原
there are grasslands close to paradise.
这是世界上生物多样性最丰富的草原
This is the most bio-diverse grassland in the world...
巴西的塞拉多草原
..the Cerrado in Brazil.
这里孕育着成千上万种独特的动植物
Here there are thousands of species of both animals and plants found nowhere else.
这个丰富多样的群落想要保持生态平衡
A rich and complex community that is kept in balance
便不能缺少这种幽灵般的生物
by this ghostly creature.
鬃狼
A maned wolf.
鬃狼安静而腼腆 它们鲜为人知 较为罕见
Quiet and shy, it's little known and seldom seen.
与世上其他狼不同
Unlike any other wolf in the world,
鬃狼以素食为主
their diet is mostly vegetarian.
其中最受鬃狼钟爱的是狼果
And they particularly like lobeira fruit.
这种植物可以增加土壤肥力
This plant increases the fertility of the land,
并有助于塞拉多草原的稳定
and helps to sustain the entire Cerrado.
尽管鬃狼看起来不像
The maned wolves, odd though it may seem,
但实际上它们是狼果这种独特植物的园丁
are, in effect, the gardeners of these unique plains.
茂密的草丛反过来为这只雌性鬃狼
The dense grass in turn provides this female
提供了一个舒适的家
with a comfortable home...
以及一个可以隐藏三只刚出生幼崽的地方
..and somewhere to hide her three puppies,
它们只有一个月大
just one month old.
鬃狼过于罕见 因此这只雌性鬃狼被戴上了无线电项圈
She is so rare that she's been fitted with a radio-collar
方便科学家进行持续的研究
so that scientists can study her continuously.
根据我们的遥控"巢穴摄像机"显示
And our remotely controlled "den camera" reveals a mother
一天中 雌性鬃狼在巢穴中哺乳幼崽的时间只有数小时
only comes here for a few hours a day to suckle her pups.
它将大部分时间都花在觅食上 以供养日益壮大的家庭
She spends much of her time foraging to provide for her growing family.
此时 单独留在巢穴中的幼崽
Now, alone in the den,
突然陷入了危险之中
her puppies are suddenly in danger.
危险并非来自于捕食者
Not from other predators...
而是来自于火灾
..but from fire.
它们的家园燃起了熊熊大火
Their home is being burnt all around them.
火情可以在数分钟内蔓延至近两公里以外
These fires can race through a mile of grassland in a matter of minutes.
塞拉多草原被摧毁了
The Cerrado devastated.
火灾原因是什么呢
Why?
是人类为了开垦土地种植庄稼
In order to clear land to grow crops.
这场大火没有波及到它们的巢穴
This particular fire didn't reach their den.
但巢穴里空空如也
But it's empty.
这一次 这一家子鬃狼很幸运
This time, the family were lucky.
但整个物种正面临着令人担忧的不确定未来
But her species faces an alarmingly uncertain future.
按照目前的栖息地破坏速度
At the current rate of habitat destruction,
这些可能将是最后一批生存于野外的鬃狼
these may be some of the last maned wolves to survive in the wild.
在草原上 动物与环境的联系十分紧密
In grasslands, the land and the animals
以至于哪怕一种关键物种灭亡
are so closely interconnected, that the loss of one key species
都很有可能引发整个生态系统的崩溃
could well trigger the collapse of the entire ecosystem.
这种悲剧正在非洲中部发生
That's what happened here in central Africa,
这里足有95%的大象因象牙而被猎杀
when 95% of the elephant population were killed for their ivory.
没有这些不可或缺的园丁
Without these essential gardeners -
生命便无法繁荣生长
life couldn't flourish.
这头雄性大象是是少数的幸存者之一
This male is one of the few survivors.
它身上依然留有过去的伤痕
He still bears the scars from his persecuted past.
但人类对象群的屠杀被及时制止了
But the slaughter was stopped just in time.
随着偷猎行为的终止
With an end to poaching,
这头雄象成为了一个日益壮大的象群中的一份子 生活在安全之中
this male is part of a growing herd that now lives in safety.
如今 人们认为这是最大的
Today, it's thought this is one of the largest groups
在野外生存的非洲象群之一
of African elephants surviving in the wild.
随着非洲象数量的恢复
As they recovered their numbers,
草原上的新苗也得以健康生长
their grazing encouraged a healthy growth of new grasses.
同时这也为其他动物创造了生存空间
And they created space for other animals...
让扎库马草原重获生机
..bringing life back to Zakouma.
如此奇迹般的转变
This miraculous transformation
表明如果大自然得以恢复平衡 生态环境将大大好转
shows what can happen if nature is allowed to restore its own balance.
阿巴卡尔是当地护林员团队的一员
Abakar is part of the team of local rangers
他们冒着生命危险保护这些大象
who risked their lives to protect these elephants.
我把它们视作家人
I see them as family
我将这头象视如己出
I think of this elephant as a son.
大象不仅仅使这片土地得以复原
And the elephants didn't just heal the land.
还做了一件没人预料到的事情
They did something no-one had anticipated.
我相信它们已经原谅了我们
I believe they've forgiven
并愿意再次信任人类
and trust us again.
随着我们对生态系统的奇异之处
As we understand more about the wonders,
生命彼此间的联系以及脆弱性有了更多的了解
the connections and the fragility of these landscapes...
我们的行为造成的后果逐渐成为了人们关注的焦点
..the consequences of our actions are thrown into sharp focus.
这表明我们迫切需要
They show we urgently need to do
尽一切努力帮助大自然自愈
everything we can to help nature heal itself.
幕后花絮
为了拍摄鬃狼
To film maned wolves,
「地球脉动」摄制组得到了巴西先驱科学家的帮助
the Planet Earth crew joined pioneering scientists in Brazil.
贝拉 如果你找到方向了请告诉我
If you get a direction, Bela, please let me know.
找到了 大概在汽车的三点钟方向
Yeah, she's like three o'clock from the car here.
800米远
Like 800 metres, too.
没有他们的帮助 我们几乎不可能追踪到鬃狼
Without their help the wolves are almost impossible to track,
更不用说在这片茂密的塞拉多草原上拍摄了
let alone film, in the dense grass of the Cerrado.
很难找到它们
It's so hard to find them,
大草原上的独居动物
they're sort of solitary animals in a huge grassland
高达一米的草跟鬃狼一样高
with sort of metre high grass, which is the same height as the wolf.
如同大海捞针
And it's like looking for a needle in a haystack currently.
如果它要前往那个方向 我们要掉头吗
Shall we turn the car around, if she's going to head that way?
应该是的
Yeah, maybe.
研究人员在追踪两只戴上无线电项圈的雌性鬃狼
The researchers have radio collared two female wolves.
两只狼都哺育有幼崽
Both have puppies.
他们希望能追踪一只狼到它的巢穴 并在里面安装远程摄像头
They hope to track one to a den and set up remote cameras inside.
得到的录像将为研究人员提供重要信息
The footage would provide the researchers with crucial information
并有助于保护这种濒危物种
and help to protect this endangered species.
它就在这附近
She's in here somewhere.
鬃狼太特别了
Maned wolf, they're so special.
更多地去了解这个物种非常重要
It's very important to understand more of this species.
越是了解 就越能保护到它们
When we get more knowledge, its getting easier to protect them.
然而其中一只雌性鬃狼的信号
But the signal from one of the females
将他们带向了一个令人担忧的方向
takes them in a worrying direction.
信号指向这片规模巨大的农田
So it's led us directly into this huge epic scale farmland,
老实说 我从没见过这么大规模的农田
the likes of which, to be honest, I've never seen before.
这表明鬃狼的自然栖息地已经寥寥无几
And it shows you what little is left of their natural habitat.
50%的鬃狼栖息地变成了农田
50% of maned wolf habitat has been lost to farmland.
无线电项圈显示它们常常误入这片陌生的土地
And the radio collars show they now regularly stray into this unfamiliar landscape.
不幸的是 研究人员在农田中发现了
Tragically, the researchers discover the body
戴有项圈的雌性鬃狼的尸体
of one collared mother wolf on farmland.
它的死因不明
The cause of her death unknown.
而它的幼崽将难以独自存活
Her puppies won't survive alone for long.
事不宜迟 研究人员动身寻找幼狼
Without delay, the researchers set out to find them.
鬃狼幼崽在这里
The puppies are here.
他们救出了五只一个月大的幼狼
They rescue five, one-month-old pups,
它们藏在草丛中
hidden in the long grass.
我们尽快出发
Let's get going
这些幼崽难以承受炎热的阳光
the puppies can't cope with the sun.
为了评估幼狼的身体情况
To assess their condition,
它们被送往急救机构
the pups are taken to an emergency rescue facility.
它脱水很严重
He's very dehydrated.
它们将受到全天候的照顾
They will be cared for around the clock,
直到它们足够强壮 可以回归野外为止
until they are strong enough to be released back into the wild.
鬃狼妈妈的死亡对每个人来说都是巨大的打击
Their mothers death is a huge blow for everyone.
对于摄制组来说 拍摄鬃狼巢穴仅剩的机会
For the crew, the only chance of filming in a den
是另一只戴有项圈的雌狼 名为诺琳尼娅
now lies with one remaining collared female known as Nhorinha.
它在更右边
She's more here to the right.
那是它吗 不是
Is that her there? No.
我看到它了 就在那里
Yep, I can see her, she's there. She's here.
找到了 找到了
Yeah, got her, got her, got her.
它在往两点钟方向走
She's coming towards two o'clock now.
离汽车50米
50 metres away from the car.
它正从树后过来 我们等一下
She's coming behind this tree in the middle here, let's wait.
看到了 看到它了
I've got her, I've got her. OK.
最终 摄制组拍到了诺琳尼娅的第一张照片
Eventually the team capture the first images of Nhorinha on camera.
终于看到我们要找的鬃狼了 太神奇了
To finally see our wolf is amazing.
借助无人机摄像头 摄制组跟踪到了它的巢穴
Using a drone camera, they follow her to her den.
无人机首次拍到了诺琳尼娅的幼崽
The drone reveals the first glimpse of Nhorinha's puppies.
天哪
Oh, my God.
诺琳尼娅在挪动幼崽
And she's moving them...
这样的举动是第一次被见证
..something that's never been witnessed before.
这太特别了 我的心都停止跳动了
This is very special, my heart stopped there, like...
不敢相信我真的在见证这一切
I can't believe what I'm really seeing here.
我们现在知道巢穴的位置了
We know where the den is now.
第二天早晨 摄制组再次来到巢穴
The following morning, they return to the den site.
他们想安装摄像头
They want to rig their cameras,
但只能在确认诺琳尼娅不在巢穴后才能安装
but can only approach when they know Nhorinha is not at the den.
它在附近吗
Is she nearby?
还没收到信号
No, no signal yet.
诺琳尼娅在一公里之外
Nhorinha is out of here, at least 1km.
对我们来说是个好消息
So it's very good news for us.
试着靠近巢穴吧
Let's try to approach it.
芭芭拉确认了诺琳尼娅离这里很远
Barbara checks that Nhorinha is away from the den,
因此摄制组可以在不打扰它的情况下进入巢穴
so the team can go in without disturbing her.
很好
Very good.
这个巢穴并不明显
The den isn't immediately obvious,
但这里没有草丛遮蔽
but the grass here is flattened,
因此他们安装了摄像头 并希望一切顺利
so they place their cameras and hope for the best.
我们大概离巢穴80米远
We're about 80m from the den.
在确保安全的前提下 这已经是最近的距离了
This is as close as we can be safely.
现在是关键时刻 开启摄像头
This is the moment of truth, we're turning them on.
拍到巢穴的实况了
And we're live,
摄像头位置没变
and the camera hasn't moved.
卢克负责守着摄像机
Luke keeps watch over the cameras,
团队其他人则继续监视诺琳尼娅的动向
while the team continue to monitor Nhorinha's movements.
没过多久 他们便停下了脚步
Before long, they are stopped in their tracks.
只见远处冒出滚滚黑烟
Just see this huge plume of smoke in the distance,
就在鬃狼一家子的巢穴后面
you know, directly behind the den where our mother maned wolf has been with her puppies.
我很着急 其他研究人员肯定也是如此
I'm quite anxious. I'm sure the other researchers are as well.
很可能是农民放的火
And the fire may well have been started by farmers,
为了开垦土地种植庄稼
in order to clear land to grow crops
用于喂养养殖的鸡和牛
that will be used to feed chicken and cattle around the world.
我们作业的地点离大火很近
The heat from the fire when we're working that close
以至于我的手臂能感觉到有火在烤
is so intense that I can feel it burning the skin on my arms.
大火蔓延速度特别快 根本逃不开
It moves so fast, there's no way you'd escape something like that.
全身上下的每个细胞都想赶紧逃离
Every single cell in your body just wants to get out of there.
但实际上这整片区域
But actually this whole place,
整片塞拉多草原 是被农田和公路包围着的
this whole Cerrado, is surrounded by farmland and roads,
所以如果仔细想一想
so, actually, when you really think about it,
野生动物根本无处可逃
the wildlife has nowhere to run.
芭芭拉以及整个研究团队度过了艰难的几周
After a difficult few weeks for Barbara and the research team...
-你好吗 情况如何 -挺好的
Hello, how you doing? How was it? It was good.
摄制组带来了些好消息
The crew have some good news for them.
那里有一只
Oh, track, there's one right there.
就现在
Right now. Yeah.
-你能看到吗 -这是实况吗 -是实况
Can you see? That's live? Yeah, yeah, that's live.
天哪
Oh, my God!
我从没见过这么可爱的小家伙
I've never see anything so cute in my entire life.
我也从来没有
No! Me neither. Me neither, guys.
瞧它正盯着摄像头
Look at this! Look, it's looking at the camera.
难以置信
Unbelievable.
这是世上第一次在鬃狼巢穴内
That's the first record in the world,
如此近距离记录幼狼的行为
so intimate inside the den.
从来没人见过
Nobody ever saw this.
如此重要物种的新信息
Such new information of such important species.
你也很激动吗 芭芭拉
You feeling emotional, Barbara?
很难不激动
It's difficult not to be.
难以用语言描述
I don't have words to describe it.
这对我来说太重要了
It's too much for me.
摄像头继续拍摄前所未有的镜头
The cameras continue to gather first-of-its-kind footage,
帮助人们深入了解鬃狼生命中极为重要的最初几周
providing insight into the all-important first weeks of a maned wolf's life.
以及至关重要的 帮助我们认识到为一代代生命
And, crucially, how much space must be protected
保护自然生态的重要性
to support future generations.
我衷心希望世上每个人都能看到
I really hope that every person in the world could see
这些动物是多么特别 多么美好 多么神奇
from their house, how special, and how beautiful, amazing these animals are.
我感到十分担忧 但并没有绝望
I feel quite worried, but not hopeless.
我会奋战每一天来帮助这些动物
I will fight every day and every year to help them.
我生在这片草原 长在这片草原
I was born in Cerrado, I grew up in Cerrado,
塞拉多草原是我的家 我必须保护她
and Cerrado, it's my home, I have to protect it.
下一集
Next time...
淡水世界
..the world of freshwater.
地球的命脉
The lifeblood of Planet Earth.
动物非凡卓绝的精彩戏码在这里拉开帷幕
And a stage for the most extraordinary animal dramas.
「栖息地探索者」生动地展现动物和它们的栖息地
Habitat Explorer brings animals and their habitats to life.
探索这个免费互动程序并制作折纸动物
Explore this free interactive and make origami animals!
前往bbc.co.uk/planetearth3
Go to bbc.co.uk/planetearth3
点击链接进入开放大学
..and follow the links to the Open University.
或者订购免费印刷版
Or to order a free printed version,
欢迎访问网站或拨打屏幕上的号码
visit the website or call the numbers on the screen.